Welcome back to JupyterLab and welcome to your first experiment with the world of Long Chain.
유피터랩에 잘 오셨습니다 긴 사슬 세계에서의 첫 실험에 잘 오셨어요
Let me just remind you one more time how important it is that you are going through these Jupyter notebooks,
다시 한번 말하지만 저처럼 주피터 노트들을 훑어보는 게 중요해요
Ideally, at the same time as I'm talking to you, you also are able to have Jupyter Lab up and you
이상적으로는 제가 여러분과 얘기하는 동시에 주피터 랩을 띄워
have it turned to week five and to this day to day two, and you're able to step through this as I step
5주 차로 바꾸고 오늘과 오늘, 그리고 오늘 2주 차로 해서 저처럼 이걸 하나씩 할 수 있어요
If that's not possible, then immediately afterwards as soon as you can, then then give this a shot.
그게 불가능하다면 그 직후에 최대한 빨리 이걸 시도해 보세요
It's so important that you experience this for yourself, particularly as we start talking about concepts
직접 경험해보는 게 아주 중요합니다 특히 텍스트 덩크나
like text chunks and then later vectors.
벡터 같은 개념에 대해 얘기할 때요
It's going to be super important that you validate what I'm saying, that you experiment with it, that
제 말의 유효성을 검사하고 실험해보고 직접 보시는 게 아주 중요합니다
you see it for yourself, and try out the code and print out various things to get very comfortable
코드를 시험해보고 다양한 걸 프린트하세요 막후에서 작동하는 방식에 아주
with the way it's working behind the scenes.
익숙해지기 위해서요
So we are, of course, in week five, in the folder we're on day two, and we're looking now at what
5주 차 폴더에 들어온 게 2일째예요 지금 보시는 건 전날의
is a bit of a copy of the previous day, but with more to come.
비트 복사본이지만 앞으로 더 나올 거예요
We do some imports and now we've got some new imports.
수입품도 있는데 새로운 것도 있네요
Our first time importing some code from Lang Chain, we're going to import some things called document
랭 체인에서 코드를 불러오는 건 처음이죠 문서 로더라는 걸 불러오겠습니다
loaders, which are utility classes which help us load in files.
파일을 불러오는 걸 도와주는 유틸리티 클래스죠
There's one called directory loader that loads in an entire folder and text loader for loading in an
디렉토리 로더라는 게 있는데 전체 폴더에 로드하는 거죠 개별 텍스트 파일을
individual text file.
로드하는 텍스트 로더요
I'm also importing something called character text splitter, which is something that's able to take
문자 텍스트 분할기라는 것도 불러오고 있어요
in, uh, and divide a document into chunks of characters, as you will see.
문서를 받아들여서 글자 덩어리로 나누는 거죠
Let's run those imports.
수입 검사 결과나 보죠
Uh, I set some constants that we're not actually going to use today, but we will do next time.
제가 몇 가지 상수를 설정했는데 오늘은 사용하지 않겠지만 다음에 쓸 거예요
Uh, and let's get to business.
Get it, get it, get it, it! 자, 그럼 본론으로 들어가죠
So you remember last time we did a hokey thing where we read in documents and put them in a dictionary?
지난번에 했던 유치한 거 기억나요? 문서를 읽어 사전에 넣는 거요 Put
The key was the name of the document.
열쇠는 문서의 이름이었어요
The value was the contents of the document.
그 서류의 내용이 가치 있는 거죠
Well, this time we're going to do something a bit smarter.
이번에는 좀 더 현명한 비트를 만들 거예요
Using lang chains help.
랑 체인을 쓰면 도움이 돼요
So we first get a list of the different folders in our knowledge base.
먼저, 지식 기반의 다양한 폴더들의 리스트를 get으로 하고요.
You'll remember those folders are these company contracts employees and products.
이 폴더들은 회사 계약직 직원들과 제품들이라는 걸 기억하실 거예요
So we put that into folders.
그래서 그걸 폴더에 넣었어요 Put
And now for each of those folders we are going to first get the type of document company contracts employees
이제 각각의 폴더에 대해 먼저 문서 유형을 갖게 됩니다 회사 계약 직원 또는 제품이요
And we are then going to load in this directory using the directory loader where you pass in the the
그런 다음 이 디렉터리를 로드합니다 디렉터리 로더를 사용해서요 그에 대한 핸들, 디렉터리
the handle to it, the directory path.
경로를 넘기는 곳이죠
And we also pass in something called the text loader loader class, which tells it that we should use
텍스트 로더 로더 클래스라는 것도 제출합니다 각각의 파일을 가져오는
that to bring in each of these files because they are text files, and it's as simple as that.
데 사용하라고 말해주죠 텍스트 파일이니까요 그렇게 간단해요
We then just call loader dot load and it will bring in all of those documents.
그런 다음 loader.load를 호출합니다 그럼 모든 문서를 갖고 오죠
Going to iterate through each of those documents.
각각의 문서를 반복하는 거죠
I'm going to say can we set the metadata on each document.
각 문서의 메타데이터를 설정할 수 있는지 묻죠
We want to add in something called doc type and set that to be the Doctype, whether it's company contracts,
doc 타입이라는 것을 추가하고 Doctype로 설정해야 합니다 회사 계약이든 직원이나
employees or products.
제품이든 간에요
And then add that to a list called documents.
그런 다음 문서라는 목록에 추가하세요
Hope that made sense.
이해하셨길 바라요
I'm going to run it and just show you that as a result of doing that, we now have 31 objects of type
실행해 보겠습니다. 그 결과로 이제 문서의 31개 객체가 생겼습니다.
document and I can show you what one of them looks like.
그중 하나가 어떻게 생겼는지 보여드릴게요.
Here it is.
여기 있네요
It is in the knowledge base directory.
지식 기반 디렉터리에 있어요
The metadata has something called source which tells you where it is.
메타데이터에는 소스라는 게 있어서 위치를 알려줘요
And then this is doctype is what we added in products.
그리고 이건 우리가 제품에 추가한 Doctype이에요
So it's a product.
그러니까 제품이죠
It's called realm MD and that is the full contents of the file.
Ermmd라고 하는데 파일의 전체 콘텐츠죠
Let's go and satisfy ourselves that if we go into products there is indeed something called realm.md.
제품에 관해 생각해 보면 렐름이라는 게 있어요 md요
And if I double click on that, we'll see presumably that it is the same thing that got loaded in.
그걸 더블 클릭하면 아마도 로드된 것과 같은 것이겠죠
We can also look at the first document here.
첫 번째 문서도 볼 수 있어요
And it's also in products.
제품에도 적용되죠
And it's called Mark calm.
마크의 침착함이죠
And there you can see where that comes from.
왜 그런 건지 아시겠죠?
And let's just pick some random number 24.
무작위로 24번을 뽑죠
The 24th one of our documents is an employee HR record for Maxine Thompson.
24번째 서류는 맥신 톰프슨의 직원 인사 기록이에요
And there is Maxine.
맥신도 있네요
She's a doc type employee and there is her contents.
문서 같은 직원이고 내용물도 있어요
So nothing very complicated.
복잡할 게 없죠
We've loaded in the documents and we've given them a doc type, and they are 31 of them sitting in documents.
문서를 넣고 문서 유형을 줬는데 그중 31명이 서류에 앉아 있어요
Next thing we're going to do is use this text splitter thing, which is going to take the the documents,
다음으로 할 일은 텍스트 분할기입니다 문서를 가져다가 각
and it's going to divide each document into chunks of characters.
문서를 문자 덩어리로 나누죠
And you specify two things to lang chain when you do this.
이걸 할 때 랑 체인에 두 가지를 지정하세요
One is the chunk size, which is roughly how many characters do you want to fit into each chunk?
하나는 덩어리 크기입니다 한 덩어리당 대략 몇 글자를 넣어야 하는가 하는 거죠
And I say roughly, because we're going to give lang chains some discretion to make sure that it that
대강이요 랑 체인에 재량권을 줄 거니까요 합리적인
it tries to split these chunks in sensible boundaries where there's a space and an empty line or something,
경계를 분할하도록 해야죠 빈 공간과 빈 줄 같은 거요 문서의 다른
or a section between different parts of the document.
부분 사이의 구역도요
So it's not cutting in the middle of a paragraph or in the middle of a word or something.
단어나 단어 중간에 컷하는 게 아니에요
That would make no sense.
말이 안 되죠
And that would result potentially in poor contacts that we'd end up providing to the LM.
그러면 잠재적으로 달 착륙선에 제공할 접촉이 좋지 않을 수 있죠
Chunk overlap says that we don't want these chunks of characters to be, uh, to, to be completely
덩어리 중첩은 캐릭터들이 서로 완전히 분리되지 않게 하는
separate from each other.
거예요
We want to have some level of overlap between them.
어느 정도 겹치게 하고 싶어요
So there's some content of the document that's in common across two chunks.
두 덩크 사이에 공통으로 있는 문서의 내용이 있어요
Uh, again, so that it's more likely if you put in a query that will will pluck out a bunch of chunks
다시 말하지만, 쿼리를 입력하면 그 쿼리와 관련된 많은 부분을 뽑아낼 가능성이
that will be relevant to that query.
더 크죠.
We don't want to to risk because of some association, because of some critical word.
어떤 연관성이나 비판적인 단어 때문에 위험을 감수하고 싶진 않아요
And it only gets included in one chunk that we don't include another chunk that's really close to it.
한 덩어리에만 포함돼요 우리가 포함하지 않는 다른 덩어리는 그것과 아주 가깝죠
That's equally important.
그것도 중요해요
So the chunk overlap gives us this way of having potentially multiple chunks that contain some of the
청크가 겹치면 잠재적으로 같은 키워드를 포함하는 여러 개의
same keywords.
청크가 생기죠
So that is a text splitter.
이게 텍스트 분할기예요
And we just say split documents and we pass in the documents.
분할 문서라고 하고 문서를 제출하죠
And if I run that it's going to to run.
이걸 실행하면 실행될 거예요
And it warns me that one of the chunks that it created, uh, has a size of 1088, which is bigger than
그리고 그 물질이 만든 덩어리 하나가 1088이라는 걸 경고해줘요 우리가 요구한 것보다
what we'd asked for.
더 크죠
And again, that's because it's trying to be smart about how it respects boundaries.
경계를 존중하는 방법을 영리하게 쓰려고 노력했기 때문이죠
Um, and so it's this, this is the decision that it has made.
그래서 이렇게 하기로 결정했어요
So if we look at how many chunks we've ended up with, we've ended up with 123, uh, chunks, 123 chunks
덩어리가 몇 개인지 보면 123개가 나왔어요 31개의 문서에서 덩어리가 123개
from our 31 documents.
나왔죠
And what we can now do is we can pick a chunk, which we pick, pick chunk number five and have a look
이제 할 수 있는 건 덩어리를 고르는 거예요 5번 덩어리를 골라요 그 덩어리를
at that chunk.
보죠
Uh, the chunk itself has metadata, just like a document had metadata.
청크 자체에 메타데이터가 있어요 문서 메타데이터처럼요
Um, it knows the source where it came from.
어디서 왔는지 알아요
And it has doc type, the doc type that we that we had set.
우리가 설정한 문서 타입이 있어요
up.
위로요
So we know that this particular chunk has been plucked from the products.
이 덩어리가 그 제품에서 분리된 거예요
Um, and it's in fact the product summary about Markham.
마컴에 관한 제품 요약본이에요
And you can see how it just starts with a new section and it ends at the end of that section.
새 섹션에서 시작해서 그 섹션의 끝에서 끝나는 걸 보실 수 있어요
So it's been careful to respect boundaries.
그래서 경계를 존중하는 데 신중해졌죠
It's got a reasonable chunk that's about a thousand characters.
대략 천 개의 글자가 들어있죠
Um, and there'll be some overlap perhaps with the chunk right before it.
바로 전 덩어리랑 겹치는 부분이 있을 거예요
Uh, see if it chose to.
그러기로 했는지 보죠
Not in this case, the chunk before it is a very small chunk.
이 경우엔 앞에 있던 게 아주 작아요
Uh, so anyway, you can you can play around and see if you can find examples of where it's possible
어쨌든, 여러분이 찾아보실 수 있어요 가능한
options where, uh, there are overlaps between chunks.
옵션들을요 청크 사이에 겹치는 거요
Um, and so have a, have that as a quick to do go in and experiment with some of these chunks.
그래서 빨리 이 덩어리를 실험해 보고 싶어요
Find out if you can get an example of where two chunks contain the same information.
두 덩크에 같은 정보가 들어 있는 예시를 Get get 해 보세요
So what we're going to do now is we're going to just inspect the Doctype metadata across these chunks
이제 이 청크를 통해 Doctype 메타데이터를 검사해 올바른 문서 형식이
and just convince ourselves that we have all the right doc types.
다 있다고 자신을 설득할 거예요
So let's just see what what we have across all of our chunks.
그럼 모든 덩어리에 뭐가 있는지 보죠
We have four doc types employees, contracts, company and products.
doc 타입의 직원, 계약서 회사, 제품은 네 가지죠
Which is good because that of course, uh, exactly matches the four directories that we read in.
좋은 거죠, 우리가 읽은 4개의 디렉터리와 정확히 일치하니까요
So that all sounds good.
다 괜찮은 것 같네요
Uh, let's now let me just, uh, let's, let's have a look to see if we were to look through each of
그럼 이제 제가 한번 살펴볼게요 이 덩어리들을 하나씩 살펴보면
these different chunks.
어떨까요?
Which chunks have the word Lancaster in it?
랭커스터라는 단어가 들어간 덩어리는요?
Lancaster.
랭커스터요
Hopefully it's familiar to you, because that is the fictitious name of our fictitious CEO of our fictitious
아시는지 모르겠지만 그건 가상의 이름이에요 가상의 회사의 가상의 CEO죠
So Lancaster is her last name.
성이 랭커스터군요
And let's see which chunks have her last name in it.
어떤 덩어리에서 그녀의 성이 나오는지 보죠
So here we go.
자, 시작하죠
Um, so the about insurance, uh, document Has her name in it, of course, as she was the founder
보험 서류에 이름이 있어요 물론 그 회사의 창립자니까요
Um, and then her HR record has Lancaster in it and the bottom of our HR record.
인사 기록에도 랭커스터가 있는데 우리 인사 기록 맨 아래예요
Also, there's some other HR notes that mentions her, uh, by last name as well.
성까지 언급된 인사부 기록도 있고요
So, uh, you probably realize this, but from the cheap and cheerful version of rag that we did last
아마 아시겠지만 지난번에 했던 싸구려 명품 버전에서는 랭커스터라는
time, one of the big problems is that it just looks for the word Lancaster.
단어만 보이는 게 큰 문제였어요
So if there's any information about the CEO that isn't reflected in the worst Lancaster, then that
최악의 랭커스터에 비치지 않는 CEO에 관한 정보가 있다면 지난 버전의
would be missed in our in our toy version from last time.
장난감에 그게 빠져 있을 거예요
And you can see that if we do a search for Avery, her first name, you'll see that we get way more
보다시피 에이버리의 이름을 검색하면 정보가 훨씬 많이 나와요 get
chunks because she's mentioned by first name all over the place.
it's name으로만 언급돼 있거든요
Um, and so, uh, yeah.
그래서... 네
And presumably also if we do CEO, we find that there's a bunch of chunks with with CEO in them as well
또한 CEO라고 적힌 부분도 많이 발견할 수 있을
that would potentially be missed if we were just, uh, looking at purely the, uh, those with the
겁니다 랭커스터라는 단어만 본다면 그 부분을 놓치게 될 수도
word Lancaster.
있죠
So it gives you a sense that doing some kind of text based search through the documents is not a great
문서를 통해 텍스트 기반의 검색을 하는 게 좋은 방법이 아니라는 느낌을 줍니다 우리가
way of doing it, and will miss important bits of context that we need to find.
찾아야 할 컨텍스트의 중요한 부분을 놓칠 수도 있고요
So what we're looking for in our vector search is something that can be smarter about the way it finds
벡터 검색에서 찾는 건 좀 더 영리하게 텍스트뿐
chunks that are relevant using not just text, but using some understanding of the meaning behind what
아니라 의미에 숨은 단어도 찾는 거죠
And that, of course, is the big idea behind Rag.
그게 바로 래그의 아이디어예요
So at this point, hopefully you are proficient with reading in documents using the text loader and
이 시점에선 여러분이 문서 읽기에 능숙하길 바랍니다 텍스트 로더와 디렉터리 로더를
directory loader and dividing them into chunks.
이용해 덩어리로 나누죠
And if you do this exercise, you'll come in and play with the different chunks and convince yourself
이 운동을 하면 다른 덩어리들을 가지고 놀면서 합리적인 부분에서 분리되었고
that they're being split in sensible places and that there's some overlap.
겹치는 부분도 있다고 스스로 확신하게 되죠
And then we'll be ready to vectorize and put in vector databases.
그런 다음 벡터화하고 벡터 데이터베이스에 넣을 준비가 되죠 Let's go